ILGWU Ohio Kentucky Region Records 5780/183
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ILGWU Ohio Kentucky Region Records
1951-1999
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union
5780/183
1 cubic feet
1 linear ft.
Records (documents).
The collection contains material relating to the activities of the office of the Ohio Kentucky Region, minutes of local union 300 between 1964 and 1968, and resolutions passed by city and state governments in the region in recognition of Garment Workers' Day, 1975. Also contains printed material either published or collected by the office, including the Ohio Kentucky Region periodical, "Ohio Kentucky News" from 1960 to 1977.
5521625
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Z. Owen, August 18, 2009
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, April 16, 2019
Biographical / Historical
The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union was once one of the largest labor unions in the United States founded in 1900 by local union delegates representing about 2,000 members in cities in the northeastern United States. It was one of the first U.S. Unions to have a membership consisting of mostly females, and it played a key role in the labor history of the 1920s and 1930s. The union is generally referred to as the "ILGWU" or the "ILG". The ILGWU grew in geographical scope, membership size, and political influence to become one of the most powerful forces in American organized labor by mid-century. Representing workers in the women's garment industry, the ILGWU worked to improve working and living conditions of its members through collective bargaining agreements, training programs, health care facilities, cooperative housing, educational opportunities, and other efforts. The ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union in 1995 to form the Union of Needle trades, Industrial and Textile Employees (UNITE). UNITE merged with the Hotel Employees and Restaurant Employees Union (HERE) in 2004 to create a new union known as UNITE HERE. The two unions that formed UNITE in 1995 represented only 250,000 workers between them, down from the ILGWU's peak membership of 450,000 in 1969.
Biographical / Historical
The ILGWU had been organizing in Cleveland since its early years, and by the 1930s, the union was organizing in other parts of Ohio and Kentucky as well. The Cleveland Joint Board and Cleveland Knitgoods Council represented workers in Cleveland, and Cincinnati Joint Board represented workers in Cincinnati and parts of Kentucky. Together, these represented ILGWU members in the Ohio-Kentucky Area.
By 1977, the Ohio- Kentucky Area, which included local unions in the Ohio-Kentucky Region, Cleveland Joint Board and Knitgoods Council, and unaffiliated locals, claimed a total membership of roughly 5,500 people. In 1978, the Ohio-Kentucky Regional Office was dissolved. Local unions in Ohio became part of the Northeast and Western Pennsylvania Department to create the Northeast, Western Pennsylvania, and Ohio Department. Kentucky locals became part of the Upper South Department.
Abraham Katovsky was the ILGWU representative in Ohio from 1910 until his death 1945. Nathan Solomon was appointed Manager of the Cleveland Joint Board, a position he held until his passing in 1948. Louis Friend and Hyman Langer served short appointments, until Nicholas Kirtzman assumed leadership of the region in 1950 and stayed in that role until his death in 1963. Sam Janis was director of the regional office from 1963 until its dissolution in 1978.
Scope and Contents
The collection documents various projects, initiatives, and efforts of the Ohio-Kentucky Region. One such example is the involvement in the spring campaign to roll back apparel and textile imports from 1985. The records include correspondence, work done to push through legislation, the organization of demonstrations for import regulations, and collaboration with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union (ACTWU), particularly Cleveland's participation in the activities. There are also notes, articles, instructions, and publicity regarding the "price watch" campaign to record prices and any changes in prices for items in stores week after week. Other such programs documented included the retraining program for laid off workers through the United Labor Agency in Cleveland.
The remainder of the collection consists of local newsletters including the "Sew it Seams," "Ohio Kentucky News" and "The Ohio Sew Biz," as well as minutes, clippings, and news and action items as they relate to Ohio and local affairs.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5780: ILGWU records 5780/183 AV: ILGWU Ohio Kentucky Region Audio-Visual Materials 5780/183 P: ILGWU Ohio Kentucky Region Photographs
Women's clothing industry -- United States.; Clothing workers -- Labor unions -- United States.; Industrial relations -- United States; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. -- Ohio-Kentucky Region.
5521625
- Spring Campaign, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Price Watch, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Unemployment, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- White Paper, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Retraining, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Move, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Reagan Budget and Women, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Scope and Contents
  March 16
- Trade Bill Agenda, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Sew It Seems, 1982-1987 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Ohio Kentucky News, 1960-1965 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Ohio Kentucky News, 1969-1977 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- The Ohio Sew Biz, 1978-1984 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Ohio-Kentucky Office Memo (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Local 300 Minutes, 1963-1968 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Senator Howard Metzenbaum, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Ohio Democratic Party, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Miscellaneous Ohio, 1951-1999 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Newspaper Clippings, 1969-1971 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Health Information and Media, 1991-1998 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Garment Workers' Day Resolution, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Ohio Kentucky News, 1960-1964 (Box 1, Folder 21)